MAX: These days we're sending around a lot of private
information through the cloud and your passwords
and credit card numbers and emails are all protected
by something called encryption.
Encryption is a way of taking information and modifying it
so that it's hard or even impossible for unauthorized
viewers to understand it.
A cipher is an algorithm for a technique
used to encrypt information.
While, modern ciphers can be very complex
and very difficult to break,
today we'll be looking at one of a
much, much older method.
You may have heard of it, it's called the Caesar Cipher.
The Caesar Cipher was named after Julius Caesar,
a famous Roman dictator who would used the Caesar Cipher
and basically shifted letters forward in the alphabet
whenever he wanted to send a secret messages to his generals.
Let's look at some of the details of this Caesar Cipher.
We'll be handing it over to Maury.
MAURY: A Caesar Cipher is an encryption technique that takes
in a normal string called a plain text and substitutes
each letter in that string with another letter that's
a fixed number of spaces
down in the alphabet.
Confused?
Let me see if I can clarify things with an example.
Let's encode, also known as encipher a plain text
into a cipher text, where all of the letters are shifted
three letters down the alphabet.
This number three is called the key.
If you write out all possible letters and letters
you'd replace it with under our key, you'd see
something like this.
Now onto the actual enciphering.
Say that our plain text is the word, lazy.
The first character in the plain text L,
would become O, since O is three letters after L.
The second character A, would become D.
Now, the third letter, Z.
What's three letters below Z?
It turns out that if you reach the end of the alphabet
when shifting down, you're supposed to wrap around.
This means that Z would become C since we wrap
around from Z to A to move one character,
one letter down and A to C to move two letters down.
And finally, the fourth letter, Y, will become B.
Now that you know how to encipher a plain text
using a Caesar Cipher you're ready to hear about
the Caesar Cipher program that you're supposed
to be writing.
Here, we pulled up our solution so we can show you
how it all should come together.
In the first part, we'll write the encipher function.
The input to this function is a plain text string
and the integer key and it returns the corresponding
cipher text.
Let's try to encipher the string lazy
with the key of three like we did before.
So let's just type that in.
Nice.
Here we have the letters, ODCB, which is exactly
the letters that we got when we did it by hand.
Then, in the second part we'll be writing
the decipher function.
Here we're given a string enciphered using a
Caesar Cipher but we're not sure what
the key is that we're supposed to use.
Your goal is to guess the key and return the deciphered
string that corresponds to that guess.
In the best case scenario that deciphered string
will be equivalent to the plain text.
Let's try to decipher this really interesting string
right here.
Nice.
It actually returned an intelligible plain text,
which is what we expect.
MAX: So, here we are in the python shell
and we're going to go over the strategy
for creating encrypt using the Caesar Cipher
as well as go over some useful functions built
into Python that you might want to use.
We recommend writing a helper function
that shifts a single letter by a given value.
So, one thing that might be useful is being able
to convert your letter to it's corresponding ASCII
valued number.
For example, ord of lowercase a, gives you 97.
Whereas, ord of lowercase z gives you 122.
The uppercase letters have different ASCII values
than lowercase letters as you can see.
And if your number is between 65 and 90,
it will be uppercase.
If it's between 97 and 122, it'll be lowercase
and if it's outside of either of those ranges,
it won't be an alphabetic character and your
Caesar Cipher shouldn't do anything to it.
Your essential strategy for converting a single letter
should be to convert it to it's number then add
your key to it.
Then, use the module operator to bring it back into
range of being lowercase or uppercase,
if it was to begin with.
And then to convert from your number back to your
new character, using the CHR, or character method.
So that will take 97 and convert it back to an a,
for example.
Then, once you have your function that takes a single
letter and shifts it by a key, you can use a list
comprehension to make a list of all your newly
enciphered letters and then you can take your list
and join it all together using Python's join function.
That should outline a pretty basic stategy for
how you'll make encipher.
So, if we're given a cipher text and we also know the key,
we can take 26 minus the key
and decipher it just like we encipher it.
However, if we don't know the key, things start
to get a little more complicated.
We can use a list comprehension to make a list
of all the possible candidate strings.
And we then wait for our code to make an educated guess
as to which one is our desired message.
Let's just say the desired message is going
to be in English.
Let's use some of the information we know about English
to take an educated guess or create a heuristic,
that let's us figure out which one is our desired message.
For example, we know that English has a lot of vowels,
so maybe the candidate string with the most vowels
might be the right one.
However, if you want to consider all of the letters,
you may have already written a function that takes the
Scrabble score of a string and we know
that in Scrabble more common letters are given
fewer points. So perhaps the string with the smallest
Scrabble score is likely to be English.
If you'd like to be more precise,
we've given you a function that takes in a letter
and gives you a frequency, or how common
it shows up in typical English.
You might find that taking the sum of the letter frequency
across the strings gives you a good estimate
of how likely that string is to be English
and then you'd take the one with the best frequency score.
Some more advanced ways that you don't quite expect involve
using dictionaries or finding which combinations of letters
are more common. However, we think that the
singular approach should work pretty well
but you're definitely encouraged to experiment
and try your own ways.
MAURY: Once you have a way of scoring a string for its
Englishness, we're now ready to put everything
together and write the decipher function.
The first thing we will need to do is create a list
comprehension that generates a list of all possible
candidate strings.
The next thing we'll need to do is use that list
in a list comprehension to create a new list.
This new list will have an element for each
candidate's string and that element
will be a list consisting of two items.
The first item is a score and the second item is
the candidate string that led to us having that score.
And then finally, we can use this new list
to find the high score and then we return
the candidate string that led us to having
that higher score. And that pretty much wraps up
how to write the decipher function.
Good luck.