SIMON: Simon here from Harvey Mudd CS5 xMOOCs.
And today we are going to be talking about list comprehensions.
Suppose we want to write a function that takes in a list,
doubles every number in that list, and then returns that list.
We could write a function to do this recursively.
This function takes in a list and returns a new list
with each element of the old one doubled.
As you can see, this isn't the most visually appealing code.
And there are better ways to write a function that does what we want.
We want to write code that does some thing, that thing being the function
of doubling to every item in a list.
And Python gives us a couple ways to actually do this.
The first is the map function.
Map takes a function and, as the name suggests,
maps it on to every element of a list.
So if we have a double function as so and we have a list like this one,
we can call map of double L and that will return a new list that
is L but with every element doubled.
So negative 5 became negative 10.
OK, this 2 over here became 4.
You can see that map indeed did double every number in f.
Map is nice, but it means you have to write a function to do anything, even
something as simple as doubling x.
A simpler way to perform a function on each element of a list
is something we call list comprehension.
For example, let's use a list comprehension
to double every number in a list.
To do this, we would use the following syntax
that you can see in the next function defined.
Let's go through what's happening here.
The first part says what we want to do to each element of our list, which
is, in this case multiply each element by 2.
For i defines what we want to call each element of our list.
In this case, we call it i, but it could really be any variable name.
Then in L tells us that i will take on each value in the list
and undergo the function we described in the beginning
of the list comprehension.
Essentially, you're telling Python to perform
a function f for each element of L.
To check if you understand this, try and write a list comprehension that
squares each element of some list L.
One list comprehension that would work to do this is x times x for x in L.
Although, there are a number of different ways you could write it.
To check if yours works, you can always test it in the Python shell.
We can also do more complex things with list comprehensions.
Suppose we want to multiply each element in a list by negative 7
if its absolute value is greater than 4.
Let's use the list range -7, 7.
To motivate this example, let's use the list range -6 to 7,
which will give us a list of all integers
from -6 to 6 inclusive.
I'll give you a syntactic hint.
To give our list comprehension a condition
at the end of the list comprehension, we write if insert condition.
Try to write this yourself.
This is what we got.
We can see that our list variable is b.
And we'll multiply each element b by -7.
The if statement tells Python that it'll only
compute the first statement if the absolute value of b is greater than 4.
If we run this, we get just as we hoped.
In summary if we want to do something to or in other words,
perform a function on everything in a list,
we can either use map or a list comprehension.
We learned how list comprehensions work by implicitly
using the map function that we also introduced to you in this video.
List comprehensions can also filter out certain values from a list.
Because of the concise syntax of list comprehensions,
they become a very powerful and flexible tool.
We highly recommend you use them when appropriate in future assignments.